<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Matt Rude's Blog</title>
    <description>Practical guides, tutorials, and insights on building powerful technology solutions without the enterprise price tag. Making technology accessible for everyone.</description>
    <link>https://mattrude.org</link>
    <atom:link href="https://mattrude.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2025 Matt Rude. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 14:15:14 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Technology</category>
    <category>Software Development</category>
    <category>Accessibility</category>
    <item>
      <title>Security on a Budget: Essential Tools and Practices</title>
      <link>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-05-01-security-on-a-budget.html</link>
      <guid>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-05-01-security-on-a-budget.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Apr 2025 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Obligatory blog post quote incoming...</p>
                
                <p>Safety expert Shayne Connolly once wryly noted on their blog: "I guess the company tag line of 'We are here for the profit, let's try not to hurt anyone' isn't great for PR though". <sup><a href="https://safetyinnovation.wordpress.com/2014/08/16/safety-is-not-a-priority-it-is-a-precondition/" target="_blank">1</a></sup></p>
                
                <p>While their cynical observation captures a harsh truth, it raises important questions about how we approach safety and security.</p>
                
                <p>This tension exists in all industries, including technology and cybersecurity. As we mark another <a href="https://archive.iww.org/history/library/misc/origins_of_mayday/" target="_blank">May Day</a>, it's clear we must take security and safety into our own hands rather than waiting for institutions to prioritize it for us. </p> 
                
                <p>We need to not only implement these practices ourselves but teach others and advocate for better security standards at all levels.</p>
                
                <p>Before diving into technical tutorials in future posts, I want to establish these essential security foundations that everyone should consider and share.</p>
                
                <h3>Zero Trust Principles</h3>
                
                <p>The concept of "Zero Trust" has transformed enterprise security, but its core principles are valuable for everyone:  <sup><a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/en-us/cybersecurity-101/zero-trust-security/" target="_blank">2</a></sup></p>
                
                <ul class="feature-list">
                    <li><strong>Do not blindly trust an individual or system</strong><br>
                    Just because something looks legitimate doesn't mean it is. From emails to applications, maintain healthy skepticism.</li>
                    
                    <li><strong>Always verify, do not trust by default</strong><br>
                    Take the extra step to confirm identities and security of systems before sharing information or access.</li>
                    
                    <li><strong>Limit the blast radius if damage is done</strong><br>
                    Compartmentalize your digital life so a compromise in one area doesn't spread to everything.</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>These principles apply universally, whether you're running a corporation or just managing your personal accounts. A practical application: assume any information you share online could potentially be leaked to anyone. This mindset helps you make better decisions about what to share and where.<br><br> The source I used for these Zero Trust principles was CrowdStrike. Ironically, people seem to have <i>zero trust</i> in them as a company after a <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/24/crowdstrike-outage-microsoft-apology" target="_blank">recent software blunder that took down airports and hospitals</a>. </p>
                
                <h3>Modern Threats: Phishing and AI Impersonation</h3>
                
                <p>Today's threats are far more sophisticated than the obvious scams of the past. Consider:</p>
                
                <ul class="feature-list">
                    <li><strong>Advanced Phishing:</strong> Attackers now research targets extensively, creating personalized messages that reference real events, colleagues, or recent activities to appear legitimate.</li>
                    
                    <li><strong>AI-Generated Content:</strong> Deepfakes now extend beyond video to voice cloning and text generation. An AI can imitate your boss's writing style or even recreate a loved one's voice asking for urgent help.</li>
                    
                    <li><strong>Multi-Platform Attacks:</strong> Sophisticated attackers coordinate across channels—starting with an email that references a legitimate text message they sent earlier.</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>The level of sophistication means you should expect attacks that:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Appear to come from trusted sources</li>
                    <li>Contain accurate personal details</li>
                    <li>Create artificial urgency or emotional pressure</li>
                    <li>Show few obvious language or formatting errors</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>(And no, I'm not describing your average cold sales call, though the similarities can be striking! The difference is that legitimate salespeople merely want your money upfront, while scammers want your credentials, identity, or both. At least the salesperson will send you something in return—even if it's just another sales person.)</p>
                
                <div class="phishing-alert">
                    <h4>🚩 Watch for Phishing Red Flags 🚩</h4>
                    
                    <p>Be alert to these common warning signs:</p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Poor grammar or spelling in messages from supposed professional sources</li>
                        <li>Urgency or unusual requests ("Act now or your account will be closed!")</li>
                        <li>Suspicious sender addresses (check the actual email address, not just the display name)</li>
                        <li>Questionable link destinations (hover before clicking to see where they really go)</li>
                    </ul>
                    
                    <p>Today's scammers particularly <b>love</b> pushing cryptocurrency investments, obscure stocks, or exotic financial schemes with promises of extraordinary returns. If someone you just met is eager to help you invest for "guaranteed" profits, your financial safety is probably not their priority.</p>
        
        <p><a href="https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-05-01-security-on-a-budget.html">View original post</a></p>
      ]]></description>
      <category>Security</category>
      <category>Tools</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Technology Is More Affordable Than Ever</title>
      <link>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-04-02-why-technology-is-more-affordable-than-ever.html</link>
      <guid>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-04-02-why-technology-is-more-affordable-than-ever.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>In <a href="https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-03-25-launching-my-personal-website.html">my previous post</a>, I mentioned how today's website costs a fraction of what similar technology would have cost in the past. This dramatic decrease in cost isn't just limited to my personal website — it's part of a broader trend in technology that has profound implications for creators, small businesses, and organizations of all sizes.</p>
                
                <p>Let's break down why tech infrastructure is more affordable and accessible than ever before, and what this means for the future of innovation.</p>
                
                <h3>The Plummeting Cost of Web Hosting</h3>
                
                <p>One of the most revealing ways to examine this trend is to look at web hosting costs over time. While raw hosting prices have remained relatively stable, what you get for your money has increased exponentially — and storage capacity provides the clearest illustration of this revolution in technology value.</p>
                
                <div class="table-section">
                    <h3 class="table-title">The Storage Revolution: More Bang for Your Buck</h3>
                    
                    <table class="storage-table">
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <th>Web Host</th>
                                <th>1998 Storage</th>
                                <th>2008 Storage</th>
                                <th>2025 Storage</th>
                                <th>10-Year Growth<br>(1998-2008)</th>
                                <th>Overall Growth<br>(1998-2025)</th>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td class="cell-webhost">Hostway</td>
                                <td data-label="1998 Storage">200 MB<sup>2</sup></td>
                                <td data-label="2008 Storage">12,000 MB</td>
                                <td data-label="2025 Storage">50 GB</td>
                                <td data-label="10-Year Growth">5,900%</td>
                                <td data-label="Overall Growth">24,900%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td class="cell-webhost">Liquid Web<sup>1</sup></td>
                                <td data-label="1998 Storage">250 MB</td>
                                <td data-label="2008 Storage">1,000 MB</td>
                                <td data-label="2025 Storage">30-960 GB</td>
                                <td data-label="10-Year Growth">300%</td>
                                <td data-label="Overall Growth">~198,000%</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td class="cell-webhost">DreamHost</td>
                                <td data-label="1998 Storage">10 MB</td>
                                <td data-label="2008 Storage">500,000 MB</td>
                                <td data-label="2025 Storage">Unlimited</td>
                                <td data-label="10-Year Growth">5,000,000%</td>
                                <td data-label="Overall Growth">∞</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table>
                    
                    <div class="table-meta">
                        <div class="table-sources">Sources: <a href="https://www.pingdom.com/blog/web-hosting-now-vs-10-years-ago/" target="_blank">Pingdom (2008)</a>, <a href="https://www.dreamhost.com/hosting/shared/" target="_blank">DreamHost (2025)</a>, <a href="https://www.liquidweb.com/pricing/" target="_blank">Liquid Web (2025)</a>, <a href="https://hostway.com/" target="_blank">Hostway (2025)</a>
        
        <p><a href="https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-04-02-why-technology-is-more-affordable-than-ever.html">View original post</a></p>
      ]]></description>
      <category>Analysis</category>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Launching My Personal Website</title>
      <link>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-03-25-launching-my-personal-website.html</link>
      <guid>https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-03-25-launching-my-personal-website.html</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Today marks an exciting milestone. I have finally launched my personal website!</p>
                
                <p>Built with vanilla HTML, CSS, and JavaScript on Cloudflare's infrastructure, this entire site costs less than $8 USD per year to own and host. A comparable WordPress site might cost $200 USD/year including domain and security certificates, plus additional fees for plugins and ongoing maintenance. This cost disparity reflects a pattern I have observed throughout my career as a software developer and data engineer: the significant gap between vendor pricing and actual implementation costs.</p>
                
                <p>This technology affordability gap scales dramatically:</p>
                
                <ul class="feature-list">
                    <li>Small organizations often spend hundreds annually on basic websites with limited customization</li>
                    <li>Mid-tier businesses invest thousands in proprietary systems while using just a fraction of their features</li>
                    <li>Enterprises commit to huge contracts for capabilities that could be built for a fraction of the cost</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>One organization I worked with saved $2400 USD annually and improved data reliability by replacing their existing synchronization process with a custom solution accelerated by AI tools. This exemplifies how modern development approaches can make specialized solutions more accessible than ever.</p>
                
                <h3>My Mission: Democratizing Technology</h3>
                
                <p>My vision is to bridge this gap by challenging two common assumptions: that powerful technology requires enterprise-level budgets, and that implementing custom solutions requires specialized expertise. The evidence increasingly suggests neither is true.</p>
                
                <p>I am creating practical resources that empower everyone, regardless of technical background or budget constraints, to implement robust technology systems by leveraging:</p>
                
                <ul class="feature-list">
                    <li>Affordable infrastructure with generous free tiers (like Cloudflare<img src="https://mattrude.org/assets/images/cloudflare-icon.svg" alt="Cloudflare" class="inline-icon" style="height: 1em; vertical-align: middle; margin: 0 2px;">)</li>
                    <li>Open source solutions that rival commercial offerings</li>
                    <li>Clean, simple code patterns that are easier to maintain</li>
                    <li>Secure design principles that protect data without specialized knowledge</li>
                    <li>AI-assisted development tools that amplify basic technical skills</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>This approach creates better, more tailored solutions that precisely match your needs rather than forcing your processes to conform to off-the-shelf software limitations.</p>
                
                <h3>What to Expect</h3>
                
                <p>To put these principles into action, I'm developing a series of practical resources that progress from fundamental to advanced implementations. Here's what you can look forward to in the coming weeks and months:</p>
                
                <ul class="feature-list">
                    <li>Practical Applications of AI Tools for Non-Technical Users</li>
                    <li>Essential Cybersecurity Practices for Small and Medium Organizations</li>
                    <li>Custom Survey and Data Collection Systems</li>
                    <li>Lightweight CRM Solutions for Small Organizations</li>
                    <li>Integration Strategies for Existing Business Tools</li>
                    <li>Data Visualization Tools and Dashboards</li>
                </ul>
                
                <p>These tutorials won't assume extensive coding experience—if you can follow instructions and have basic computer literacy, you can implement these solutions. I will emphasize how modern code patterns combined with AI tools can make development accessible to non-specialists while creating technology that truly serves everyone's needs.</p>
                
                <p>While these resources will empower many readers to build their own solutions, I recognize that some situations call for more direct collaboration. That's why I am also offering several ways we can work together...</p>
                
                <h3>Working Together</h3>

                <!-- NEW: Reformatted as cards for better visual balance -->
                <div class="service-cards">
                    <div class="service-card">
                        <h4>Full-Service Development</h4>
                        <p>We define your requirements together, then I handle all development and hosting. You get a complete, worry-free solution with ongoing support—ideal if you want to focus on your core mission without technical concerns.</p>
        
        <p><a href="https://mattrude.org/blog/posts/2025-03-25-launching-my-personal-website.html">View original post</a></p>
      ]]></description>
      <category>Introduction</category>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>